Just one place... just one place...
tatta hitotsu tatta hitotsu no...
Just one of me... just one of me...
tatta hitori tatta hitori no...
I'm right here.
watashi wa koko
With a chest made of rubble, I can't even breathe.
gareki no mune iki mo dekinai
The rain starts to fall, like a slumbering cry.
furidasu ame nemuru you ni cry
What flower should I decorate myself with
kono sekai o ikinuku no naraba
To stay alive in this world?
donna hana o kazareba ii no?
I want to believe, but still can't manage it...
shinjitai kuse ni shinjirarezu ni
My powerless and pointless self
muryoku de muimi na jibun ga
Still embraces my heart.
soredemo kokoro de idakun da
I can hear a voice calling to me, saying, "Come this way!"
"kocchi e oide" to koe ga kikoeru
A limitless and reckless tomorrow
mugen de mubou na ashita ga
Will still be waiting for me somewhere.
soredemo dokoka de matsu kara
Just one place... just one place...
tatta hitotsu tatta hitotsu no...
Just one of me... just one of me...
tatta hitori tatta hitori no...
I'm right here.
watashi wa koko
I can't find the will to do anything.
（エリアス）
何もする気が起きない
It's summer.
夏だし やることは
いろいろあるはずなんだけど…
There should be plenty to do.
She only needed to be an apprentice as a pretense.
（エリアス）
見せかけの弟子でよかった
So I bought her without much thought,
and I observed her without much thought.
だから 適当に買って
適当に観察して
I didn't think I'd need to do much more.
それだけでいいと思って…
She was quite unusual,
珍しい質(たち)の その子は
and she was surprisingly quick to warm up to me.
意外にも素直に僕に懐いてくれた
でも…
But...
She doesn't speak much.
彼女は あまりしゃべらない
Seeing her that way, I'm filled
with two indescribable sensations.
それを見ると
説明できない感覚が２つ湧き上がる
Elias...
（チセ）エリアス…
I was asleep.
寝てた
It's done?
出来てた…
（リンデル）出来たか？
Is it done?
うわっ！ リンデルさん
Lindel-san.
Then let's add the final touches.
ならば 仕上げをしようかの
You become sleepy because you've
unknowingly been using your magic.
（リンデル）
眠くなるのは 知らず知らず
魔力を使っておるからだ
The things we make are imbued with magic.
だから 我々が作るものには
魔力がこもるのよ
Ainsworth should have taught you these things.
本来ならば こういうことは
エインズワースが
教えるべきなんだがの
私が聞けないのが悪いんです
It's because I can't ask him.
I don't like giving him trouble.
面倒かけたくなくて
いたっ…
Taking care of youngsters doesn't even count as trouble.
ひよっこの世話なんぞ
面倒のうちにも入らんわ
You have no idea how much
of a pain in the ass he's been.
わしなど あれに
何度 手を焼かされたか
何年たってもスキーは下手だし
スープも焦がす
Years went by, but he still was
terrible at skiing, his soup was always burnt,
力加減も覚えんし
火すら満足に扱えんし
he never learned to restrain himself,
and he could never handle fire adequately.
チセのほうが
よほど覚えがよくて器用だ
You're far more deft and quick to learn.
What is that bonehead even...
そもそも あの骨は…
Now, then, with your hair and this...
（リンデル）さて…
おぬしの髪と これ
（チセ）宝石？
Gems?
I was given these by an acquaintance a long time ago.
かなり前に知人にもらったものだ
These stones are said to have been bathing
湖の底で千年
月の光と日の光を浴びた石だそうだ
in sunlight and moonlight for a
thousand years at the bottom of a lake.
They're shining.
光ってる…
It's dim, but it ought to be enough
to light the ground beneath your feet.
（リンデル）
淡いが 足元を照らす
しるべくらいにはなるだろう
Iruna Etelero
Nadia, Ezelevoteh
Lezelkoh, Mikemesta
Iruna Etelero
Satoa, Aimeltewa
Lezelkoh, Mikemesta
Ahmeruh, Mikelmoh
Toimessez, Mikelmoh
Masseri, Imekuwozeh
Towonnah, Mizaimesta
Kessellah, Kessellah
Kessellah, Sehtoru
Ahmelva, Etelerovoh
I took the liberty of wrapping it around the outside.
（リンデル）
少し装いに回させてもらった
It has a beautiful sunset color, after all.
きれいな夕日の色をしているからの
これが おぬしの杖だ
This is your wand.
Take good care of it.
大事にしやれよ
（チセ）はい…
Okay.
Where am I?
ここは…
（ネヴィン）やあ
Hello, little mage. It has been some time.
久しぶりだね 小さな魔法使い
You're...
（チセ）あなたは！
（ネヴィン）
私の枝を杖にしてくれて
ありがとう
Thank you for turning my branch into your wand.
I'll use it well.
大事に使います
Where are we?
ここは どこですか？
どうして ここに…
Why are we here?
（ネヴィン）
杖によって
君と私に縁(えにし)の糸が結ばれたから
Because we've established a
bond of fate through the wand.
A bond of fate?
（チセ）縁の糸？
（ネヴィン）ここは境目
We're at the border between
travelers and those whose travels have ended.
旅人と 旅を終えた者
Those on the other side and those on this side.
あちら側の者 こちら側の者
Those whose paths never meet can intersect here.
決して交わらぬ者が
交錯を許される道
So this is how it appears to your eyes.
君の目には こう見えるのか
What a beautiful path.
美しい道だ
Does it appear differently to your eyes?
あなたの目には
違って見えるんですか？
I am already dead.
（ネヴィン）私は既に亡き者
I depend on the vision of your excellent eyes.
よく見える君の目に頼っているのさ
You always appear unhappy, Chise.
（ネヴィン）
君は いつも
浮かない顔をしているね チセ
How about it?
どうかな？
All that's here is an old geezer.
ここは老いぼれしかいない
Why don't you try talking to yourself out loud?
独り言でも吐き出してみては？
I've become greedy.
（チセ）
私は… 欲張りになっちゃった
最初は いつ放り出されても
いいやって思ってたはずで
At first, I was content knowing I
might get kicked out at any moment.
So I tried not to depend on him.
だから 頼らないようにしてて…
I was comfortable, because
I knew he thought nothing of me.
あのヒトが私のこと
どうとも思ってないから安心できて
Because he called me family, even if it was only for show.
家族だって
見せかけでも言ってくれたから
But...
でも…
いつの間にか エリアスが…
at some point, it began to upset me
that he—Elias—wouldn't talk to me.
あのヒトが話してくれないのが
不満になって
さみしくて
I became lonely and scared.
怖くて…
I don't know why I couldn't stay distant.
なんで興味がないままで
いられなかったのかな
そうすれば 多分
不満なんて持たなくてよくて
That way, I wouldn't have had to be worried.
いつ放り出されても
諦められたはずなのに…
I could have given up, no
matter when he'd thrown me out.
（ネヴィン）
独り言に返すのは不粋なのだけどね
I realize it's tasteless of me to
respond when you're just talking to yourself.
But is your Elias someone who
would suddenly throw you out?
君のエリアスは
突然に君を放り出すなんてことを
するヒトなのかい？
Has he said such a thing?
そんなことを言ったりしたのかい？
Has anything happened, even
once, to give you cause for worry?
（ネヴィン）
チセが恐れることが
一度だって起こったことが？
No.
（チセ）ない…
Then you need to stop
worrying as though the sky is falling.
（ネヴィン）
なら 天が落っこちる心配を
するようなことは やめなさい
でも…
But he might change his mind, even if he's okay now.
今は よくても
気が変わるかもしれない
He might get bored of me.
私なんか
すぐ飽きられるかもしれない
Just like she did.
あのヒトも
いらなくなったら きっと…
Once he doesn't need me...
Shall I speak aloud to myself, too?
（ネヴィン）私も独り言を話そうか
I'm thankful to Chise's mother and father.
私はチセの母君と父君に
感謝をしている
When a creature is struggling to
survive, it often abandons or kills its young.
（ネヴィン）
己が生きるのに厳しいとき
獣の親は
子を見捨てたり 殺したりする
If it can stay alive, it can have another child someday.
生き残りさえすれば
また次の子を産めるからだ
Still, Chise's mother released her hands off of her neck.
でも チセの母は
チセの首から手を離した
Why?
どうしてだろう？
どうして そのまま
チセを手にかけなかった？
Why did she not kill Chise?
Why did she kill herself instead, despite
wishing she hadn't given birth to Chise?
産まなければよかったと
泣いておいて
どうして 己を絶ったんだろう
How would I know?
（チセ）分からない… そんなの
Because Chise came to see me, I spent
my last moments flying through the sky.
（ネヴィン）私は…
チセが来てくれたおかげで
最期に空を飛べた
チセのおかげで救われた人や
獣たちがいた
There were people and
creatures that were saved by Chise.
A child was saved because Chise called them over.
チセが おいでと言ったおかげで
救われた子もいる
己を
ほいほいと捨てられるものみたいな
To value oneself so little, as though one were disposable,
そんなふうに低く見るということは
is to say that those of us
they've saved are just as worthless.
君に救われた我々を
どうでもいいものと言ってるのと
同じだよ
そんなこと…
That's not...
私は… でも…
I...
I wasn't even trying to do that.
そうしようと思って
やったわけでもないのに…
Be that as it may,
（ネヴィン）たとえ そうでもね
there are times when a simple word
spoken or a hand offered saves another.
ほんのわずかな言葉や手のひらが
誰かを救うこともあるんだよ
だから 私は
君に己を誇ってほしいと思っている
So I find myself wanting you to be proud of yourself.
You yourself, because you were
able to offer your hand to someone.
誰かに手を差し伸べることができた
君自身を
And I thank your mother and
father for leaving you with us.
そして
そんな君を残した母君と父君に
感謝している
Nevin...
（チセ）ネヴィン…
You said my name.
（ネヴィン）
名を呼んでくれるのかい
ありがとう
Thank you.
リンデルにもらった
すてきな名なんだ
It's a lovely name given to me by Lindel.
Hatori Chise,
羽鳥智世(はとりちせ)
you are free.
君は自由だ
Even if you should be burdened by a curse
and eventually fall, that, too, is your choice.
君が呪いを抱えて生きても
その末に いつか堕(お)ちても
全ては君の自由なんだ
Therefore, I want you to think—not for
another—but about what you want to do.
だから 誰かのためでなく
君自身が どうしたいかを
考えてほしい
（ネヴィン）その杖は私の杖
That wand is my wand.
No matter where you are, it will light your way.
どこにいても君の行く道を照らす
You can go anywhere.
君は どこにでも行けるんだ
Myself, Lindel, even that child of thorns...
私もリンデルも あの茨(いばら)の子も
何もかもが つながっていて
Everything is connected, and all will
return here to set forth on a new journey.
全ては等しく ここへ戻り
また旅に出る
（チセ）ネヴィ…
Nevin...
（ネヴィン）しばしのお別れだ
It's only a brief farewell.
Oh, right, you should be quick to
say what you wish to say or hear.
言いたいことも聞きたいことも
すぐ言葉にしたほうがいい
Some words ripen with age,
but some also lose their color.
言葉は
時がたつほどに熟れていくが
色を失っていくものでもある
からね…
（リンデル）チセ
Chise.
チセ？
You seemed out of it.
ぼうっとしておったようだが
大丈夫か？
Are you all right?
I met with Nevin.
（チセ）ネヴィンに会いました
With Nevin?
（リンデル）ネヴィンに？
Thank you for the wand and shelter.
（チセ）
杖と寝床を
ありがとうございました
I have to return home right away,
すぐに帰らなければ
ならなくなったので
so I'll be going now.
帰ります
I'd like to thank you later.
お礼は また今度させてください
I don't mind, but what's happened?
それはいいが…
どうした？ いきなり
There's something I want to tell Elias.
エリアスに伝えたいことがあるので
せっかく背中を押してもらったので
頑張ってみようかと思って
I want to make the best of
the encouragement he gave me.
そうか
All right.
では グィーを呼んでこよう
I'll call Gwee.
ルツ！
Ruth.
Chise.
（リンデル）チセ？
I can go anywhere.
（チセ）
どこにでも行ける
Everything is connected.
全ては つながっている
なら…
Then...
お願い　あのヒトの所へ つないで
Please.
Connect me to him.
（火の精Ａ）行くの？
Are we going?
We're flying.
（火の精Ｂ）飛ぶんだ
I'll help you.
（火の精Ｃ）助けてあげる
（火の精Ｄ）貸してあげる
I'll give you a hand.
Let's fly there.
飛んでいこう
世界を巡る炎の翼で！
The wings of flame will take us around the world.
On these wings...
（チセ）翼で…
いやはや…
Oh, dear.
I thought she was a quiet girl,
but she might actually be a wolverine.
おとなしい娘と思っていたが
もしかすると クズリかもしれんな
Chise.
（エリアス）チセ？
I was supposed to come home the way you do,
（チセ）
ほ… 本当は エリアスみたく
帰ってくるはずだったんですけど
but the fairies were...
妖精たちが…
え… えっと
杖が出来たから早く帰ろうと思って
I... I mean, my wand's finished,
so I wanted to come home early.
So I got their help and used magic.
ちゃんと助けてもらって
魔法を使えました
See? Lindel-san finished it for me, too.
ほら ちゃんとリンデルさんにも
仕上げをしてもら…
You sure are pretty reckless.
（エリアス）
ホント
結構むちゃなことするよね 君…
Welcome home, Chise.
おかえり チセ
ただいま帰りました エリアス
I'm home, Elias.
I thought so.
（エリアス）やっぱり！
Do you have any idea how far the land of dragons is?
ドラゴンの国から
どれだけあると思ってるのさ
You're an idiot to try to come by magic.
魔法で飛ぶなんて
バカにも程があるよ
（チセ）
バカ…
An idiot...
（チセ）杖もあるし 大丈夫かと…
I thought I'd be fine, especially with the wand.
（エリアス）
いいから ひと眠りしな
Just get some sleep.
（チセ）
早く…
But...
言いたいことが… あるのに…
I can't wait to tell him.
It's warm.
（エリアス）ぬくいなあ
Mom.
（幼いチセ）
お母さん… お母さん
Mom.
怖いのがいる
There's a scary thing.
You're right.
（チセの母）そうね
You can't let it scare you, though.
だけど 怖がっちゃダメよ
The more scared you are, the more you'll attract.
怖がったら
もっと寄ってきちゃうから
（幼いチセ）でも 怖い…
But I'm scared.
Don't worry.
（チセの父）
大丈夫
お父さんがいれば寄ってこない
Dad will keep them away.
（チセの母）
そう言って あなた
最初は腰抜かしたじゃないの
You say that, but you were scared stiff at first.
（チセの父）うるせえ！
Shut up!
（チセの母）
チセは もう お姉ちゃんだから
できるよね
You're a big sister now, Chise. You can handle it, right?
Yeah.
Good for you, Chise.
偉いね チセ
Good girl.
偉いね…
I was dreaming.
夢…
お母さん 泣いてなかった
Mom wasn't crying.
怒ってもなかった
She wasn't even angry.
あんなこと あったんだな…
I forgot that had even happened.
（綿蟲(わたむし)たち）
メエ メエ メエ メエ…
Morning, Chise.
（ルツ）おはよう チセ
（チセ）ルツ おはよう…
Morning, Ruth.
これ 何事？
What's going on?
Oh, this is bad.
（ルツ）ああ 大変だな
早く散らばってくれないと
追いかけたくなる
They need to get lost. My urge to chase them is rising.
あ… そっち？
Oh.
It looks like you had a good dream.
（ルツ）
悪くない夢を見ていたみたいだな
Yeah.
Stare...
（シルキー）じい〜
おはよう シルキー
Morning, Silky.
Chise.
（エリアス）チセ！
Morning.
おはよう
おはようございます エリアス
Good morning, Elias.
（エリアス）
２日で目が覚めてくれて助かったよ
Good thing you woke up in just two days.
（チセ）これは？
What's going on?
（アエトニキ）アエ〜
（エリアス）毛刈りの時期だ
It's shearing season.
（チセ）
不思議だな
It's strange.
（アエトニキ）
アエ アエ アエ アエ
アエ？
（チセ）
少し前までは 自分が
こんな温かい場所にいることなんて
Until just recently, I could have never
imagined being in such a warm place.
想像もできなかったのに…
だけど
But...
今は…
Now...
（エリアス）チセ
Chise.
は〜い
Coming.
（チセ）おいしい
Delicious.
To keep the seeds I tie to this branch
eda ni musubu mi ga jukusu mae ni
From falling before they ripen
ochite shimawanu you
I bloom again in profusion, painfully
kurushii hodo ni mata sakimidareru
To connect myself to tomorrow.
asa e tsunagu you
Even as they're born again
nando kurikaeshi
And again,
kurikaeshi umaretemo
I'll always show them
itsumo atarashii
A brand new sky.
sora o misete ageyou
I'll pen a story that no one,
daremo mada daremo
No one has ever written.
kaitenai monogatari
On a map so white, pure white,
shiroi masshiroi
I'll draw it out, singing it aloud.
chizu ni kaite utaou
The girl returns to the mage, and the story begins anew.
（チセ）
魔法使いのもとに帰った少女
物語は新たな時を刻みだす
月夜の来訪者が
彼女にもたらしたのは…
What does the visitor in the moonlit night bring?
Is the master of the house available?
（灰の目）
屋敷の主人は ご在宅であろうか？